Loretta J. Ross Papers, 1956-2005
Sophia Smith Collection
Loretta J. Ross papers
1956-2013
Ross, Loretta J.
MS 504
70 boxes (34.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Reproductive rights advocate, Civil rights activist, Feminist, Women's health activist. Papers contain speeches, writings, correspondence, organization and conference files, and audiovisual materials. The collection pertains primarily to Ross' activism for reproductive justice rights for women of color, anti-violence, international human rights work, and particularly to issues related black women's health. Other topics include abortion, women's health, teenage pregnancy, housing, socialism, and South Africa. Organizations represented include the Center for Democratic Renewal, National Black Women's Health Project, National Women Health Network, National Center for Human Rights Education, National Organization for Women, Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights, American Friends Service Committee, International Council of African Women, and Women's Global Network on Reproductive Rights.
Loretta June Ross was born in Temple, Texas, August 16, 1953, the sixth of eight children in a blended family. Her mother, who brought five older children to her marriage with Ross, had been owner of a music store and a domestic worker; she was a housewife as Loretta was growing up. Loretta's father, who hailed from Jamaica, was an Army weapons specialist and drill sergeant. After retiring from the military in 1963, he worked for the Post Office and often held additional jobs to support the family.
Loretta attended integrated schools - Army schools through second grade, then public schools. She was double-promoted in elementary grades and was an honors student in high school. When Loretta was 11 years old, a stranger beat and raped her. At age 15 she was the victim of incest by a distant relative; she gave birth to a son, Howard, in April, 1969. Because she chose to keep her child, she lost a scholarship to Radcliffe College.
Soon after enrolling at Howard University in 1970, Ross became involved in black nationalist politics and tenant organizing in Washington, D.C. She joined the D.C. Study Group, a Marxist-Leninist discussion group, and the South Africa Support Project. She became a founder of the National Black United Front and an officer of the City Wide Housing Coalition (1974-80). The murder of her friend and political colleague Yulanda Ward in November 1980, which she considers a political assassination, is a turning point in her life.
Sterilized by use of the Dalkon Shield at the age of 23, Ross found her way to reproductive rights and anti-violence activism. She became one of the first women to win a suit against A.H. Robins, manufacturer of the device. In 1979 she became director of the D.C. Rape Crisis Center, the only center at the time run primarily by and for women of color. In that capacity she organized the first National Conference on Third World Women and Violence in 1980. While serving as Director of Women of Color Programs for the National Organization for Women (1985-89), she organized women of color delegations for the pro-choice marches NOW sponsored in 1986 and 1989, and organized the first national conference on Women of Color and Reproductive Rights in 1987. In response to the Supreme Court's Webster decision in 1989, Ross co-coordinated production of the pathbreaking statement "We Remember: African American Women Are For Reproductive Freedom." As Program Director for the National Black Women's Health Project (1989-90), she coordinated the first national conference of African American women for reproductive rights. From 1980 to 1988, she was a member of the D.C. Commission on Women.
From 1991 to 1995, Ross was National Program Research Director for the Center for Democratic Renewal (formerly the National Anti-Klan Network), where she directed projects on right-wing organizations in South Africa, Klan and neo-Nazi involvement in anti-abortion violence, and human rights education in the U.S. In 1996 she created the National Center for Human Rights Education, a training and resource center for grassroots activists aimed at applying a human rights analysis to injustices in the U.S.
Active internationally, Ross is a founding member of the International Council of African Women and of the Network of East-West Women. She has been a regular participant in International Women and Health Meetings and helped organize the delegation of 1100 African American women to the International Conference on Population and Development in Cairo in 1984. She attended United Nations Women's Conferences in Copenhagen, Nairobi, and Beijing.
Ross has served on numerous boards (including National Women's Health Network, SisterLove Women's AIDS Project, Men Stopping Violence) and testifies on women's health and civil rights issues before Congress and the UN as well as via such national media as the Donahue Show and Pacifica News Service. She publishes on the history of abortion in the black community and is co-author of Undivided Rights: Women of Color Organize for Reproductive Justice (2004). Ross is completing a bachelor's degree at Agnes Scott College.
Ross was co-director for women of color for the April 2004 March for Women's Lives. In January 2005, she became National Coordinator of the SisterSong Women of Color Reproductive Health Collective, a growing network of Native American, Latina, African American, Asian American and other women of color groups. SisterSong's mission is to connect reproductive rights to human rights. SisterSong promotes reproductive justice through a combination of the Self-Help approach to internalized oppression and the human rights approach to structural inequity.
For more biographical information see Loretta Ross' oral history, part of the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project.
The Loretta J. Ross Papers contain speeches, writings, correspondence, organization and conference files, subject files, periodicals, memorabilia and audiovisual materials. The papers pertain primarily to her activism for reproductive justice rights for women of color, anti-violence, and international human rights work. The collection is particularly strong in issues related to black women's health. Other topics include abortion, women's health, teenage pregnancy, housing, socialism, South Africa, and national political activities. Organization files include printed material, board meeting documents, correspondence, memorabilia and notes that document the numerous organizations that Ross founded and was active in, as well as related organizations on which she collected information. They include the Center for Democratic Renewal, National Black Women's Health Project, National Women Health Network, National Center for Human Rights Education, National Organization for Women, Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights, American Friends Service Committee, International Council of African Women, and Women's Global Network on Reproductive Rights.
This collection is organized into ten series:
SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS, 1956-2004
SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1956-2005
SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES, 1956-2005
SERIES IV. ORGANIZATION FILES, 1938-2002
SERIES V. CONFERENCES AND EVENTS, 1986-2003
SERIES VI. SUBJECT FILES, 1961-1997
SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS, 1983-2001
SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA, 1982-94
SERIES IX. PERIODICALS, 1978-1999
OVERSIZE MATERIALS
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection without any additional restrictions. Access to audiovisual materials may first require production of research copies.
Additional Formats
The video and audio tapes from the Loretta Ross Papers have been digitized and are available online (on-campus access only)
Loretta Ross donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2004.
Abortion -- Political aspects -- History -- Sources; African American women -- Biography -- Sources; African American women health reformers -- History -- Sources; African American women -- Health and hygiene -- History -- Sources; African American women -- Social conditions -- History; African Americans -- Civil rights -- History -- Sources; Birth control -- Law and legislation -- History -- Sources; Feminists -- United States -- Biography -- Sources; Health care reform -- History -- Sources; Human rights -- United States -- History -- Sources; International cooperation -- History -- Sources; Reproductive health -- Developing countries; Rape -- United States -- History -- Sources; Reproductive rights -- History -- Sources; Women in development -- International cooperation -- History -- Sources; Women's health services -- United States -- History -- Sources
The full transcript of Loretta Ross' oral history is available online as part of the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project
Video and audio tapes from the Loretta Ross Papers have been digitized and are available online (on-campus access only)
More video featuring Loretta Ross:
Loretta Ross featured in "Makers" series (PBS)
Basic Skills of Organizing for Social Justice Workshops at Smith College, February 2013 (on-campus access only)
Additional materials relating to Loretta Ross can be found in the following collections:
Black Women's Health Imperative Records (formerly the National Black Women's Health Project)
National Women's Health Network Records
Reproductive Justice For All Conference Records
SisterSong Records
Undivided Rights Book Project Records
Voices of Feminism Oral History Project
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS, 1956-2004; .5 linear ft.
  This series consists of articles and clippings, biographical sketches, interviews, calendars and date books, diary and notes from Ross's Philippine trips (1988, 1990), notes, and miscellaneous biographical material. Also included in the series are personal, family, and professional. photographs (1956-94).
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE, 1956-2005; .5 linear ft.
  The CORRESPONDENCE series is arranged by date and consists of letters and greeting cards received and sent by Ross.
- SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES, 1956-2005; 1 linear ft.
  WRITINGS AND SPEECHES consists of typed and printed material, notes, flyers and posters advertising speeches, and related correspondence. The writings and speeches are arranged by title. In the cases where she wrote for a specific organization or conference, there may be duplicates in the related files in SERIES IV. ORGANIZATION FILES and SERIES V. CONFERENCES AND EVENTS series. There is also related material in SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
- SERIES IV. ORGANIZATION FILES, 1938-2002; 15 linear ft.
  ORGANIZATION FILES consists of printed material, board meeting documents, correspondence, memorabilia and notes. It is arranged alphabetically by organization title and includes organizations that Ross founded, was active in, as well as miscellaneous organizations on which she collected information. There are multiple organizations in most folders. They range from Church Women United to Anarchist Black Cross and cover a wide spectrum of subjects including reproductive rights, foundations, housing, socialism, and national political parties. Conferences and events sponsored by the larger organizations (National Black Women's Health Project, National Women's Health Network, and National Organization for Women) are located in this series. Ross's writings for these organizations have, when possible, been duplicated in SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES. Of particular interest are Center for Democratic Renewal, National Black Women's Health Project, National Women Health Network, National Center for Human Rights Education, and National Organization for Women. There is also substantial amounts of material on The Religious Coalition for Abortion Rights, American Friends Service Committee, International Council of African Women, and Women's Global Network on Reproductive Rights. There is related material in SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS
- SERIES V. CONFERENCES AND EVENTS, 1986-2003; 3 linear ft.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title and contains correspondence, printed material and memorabilia. It includes conferences and events that Ross attended, organized, and was principle speaker for, as well as miscellaneous flyers she received. Dates for this series reflect the date of the conference not necessarily the dates in the folders. There is also related audiovisual material in SERIES VII.
- SERIES VI. SUBJECT FILES, (1961-1997); 6 linear ft.
  This series consists of printed material collected by Ross both personally and in connection with organizations and conferences with which she was involved. It is arranged alphabetically, and represents a wide variety of issues. There is similar material in SERIES IV., particularly in the National Organization for Women, National Women's Health Network, and Center for Democratic Renewal. There is substantial material on abortion, birth control, countries and regions (especially South Africa and the Philippines), reproductive health, reproductive rights, teenage pregnancy, Yulanda Ward.
- SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS, 1983-2001; 2 linear ft.
  This series contains 109 audiotapes and 31 videotapes. These include 31 numbered audiotapes on various subjects, audio-videotapes from conferences, including speeches and interviews.
  The video and audio tapes from the Loretta Ross Papers have been digitized and are available online (on-campus access only)
  [NOTE: Original AV materials are closed]
- SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA, 1982-1994; 1 linear ft.
  This series contains awards, buttons, rolodex and address cards, phone messages and business cards, as well as miscellaneous items.
- SERIES IX. PERIODICALS, 1978-1999; 2 linear ft.
  This series consists of miscellaneous periodicals which are arranged alphabetically by title. There are also two folders of single issues.
- SERIES X. OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  There are 45 posters located in Flat File drawer 33.
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Articles, clippings 1969, 1990-2000, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards, [see SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA]
    - Biographical sketches and publications lists 1988-2004, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Interviews
      - Stanlie M. James 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Miscellaneous 1989-98 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Family material 1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Calendars and books 1989-2002 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
    - Charles Bannermann Memorial Fellowship Application 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Diary and notes from Philippine trips 1988, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Notes, [see also SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES]
      - Phone messages and miscellaneous memos, [see also SERIES VIII. MEMORABILIA] (Box 1, Folder 11)
      - Things to do lists 1988-2001, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Miscellaneous 1985-95, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Miscellaneous notebooks 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - University of Wisconsin Activist in Residence 1991-92 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Miscellaneous personal items undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Photographs 1956-94, undated (Box 2, Folder 6-8)
- SERIES II. CORRESPONDENCE
  - 1985-96, undated (Box 2, Folder 9-12)
  - 1985-96, undated (continued) (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
- SERIES III. WRITINGS AND SPEECHES, [see also SERIES VII. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS]
  - "ABCs of Feminism" proposal 1994 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - "Abortion Terrorists: Guerrillas in the Midst" in Front Line Feminism 1994 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "African American History and Abortion: A Neglected History" in the Journal of Health Care for the Poor and Underserved 1992 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - "African American Women and Abortion 1800-1970" (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - "African American Women's Activism in the Global Arena" in Still Lifting Still Climbing: Contemporary African American Women's Activism. Ed. Kimberly Springer, NYU Press 1999 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - "African Americans, Hate Groups and the First Amendment" 1994 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "The Assassination of Yulanda Ward: The Connections are Clear" draft 1981 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Believers in the Georgia Flag" 1993 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Black Women and Abortion" 1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Black Women Challenge the Women's Movement" 1985 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Black Women Speak Out on Abortion" report from "Between Our Selves" forum February 8, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - "Black Women: Why Feminism?" 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "Black Women's Abortion Experiences Across Cultures" undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Blacks and Feminists: A Long, Tentative Partnership" in Point of View 1988 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Breaking the Conspiracy of Silence, Preaching the Gospel of Sisterhood" draft undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Bridging a Short Gap to the Caribbean" in National NOW Times 1989 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Bringing Human Rights Home: Human Rights Education for the 21st Century" in Social Education 1998 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Building a Movement Against Racism" draft 1988 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Dangerous Intersections: Feminist Perspectives on Population, Immigration and the Environment" Conference Report, Union Theological Seminary October 25-26, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "A Distinct Consciousness: The History of Black Women and Abortion" undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "Domestic Violence and the Black Community," c. 1980-81 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "Family Planning Assistance in Africa: Futurists, Feminists, and Fundamentalists" in Critical Social Issues 1987 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - "Fascism's Comeback in Eastern Europe" 1991 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - "Faye Wattleton: A Life on the Line" undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "Filipino Women Challenge Status Quo" in National NOW Times 1988 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "The Global Women's Movement" at the University of Wisconsin at Madison February 7, 1998 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Hate Groups, African Americans, and the First Amendment" in "The Price We Pay: The Case Against Racist Speech, Hate Propaganda, and Pornography." Eds. Laura Lederer and Richard Delgado 1995 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Holding Faith with the Sun: Women, Health and Justice" 1993 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "How to Get the Goods on the Right: A Tactical and Strategic Guide" in On the Issues 1997 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "Human Rights Education in the United States" 1995 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "Human Rights Education to Counter the Right" undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - "Image and Reality: The Hidden Agenda of the Anti-Choice Movement" 1992 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - "The Impact of Webster on Women of Color" in National NOW Times 1989 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - "In Pursuit of Perfect Choice: Feminism and Reproductive Technology" in Health/PAC Bulletin 1992 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - "Just Choices: Women of Color, Reproductive Health and Human Rights" in "Policing the National Body: Race, Gender and Criminalization" eds. Jael Silliman and Anannya Bhattacharjee 2002 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - "The Klan in Court" 1992 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - "Lesbians, Gays Must Be Active Participants in New Human Rights Paradigm" in La Voz de Esperanza 1998 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - "List of Qualities in a Feminist Leader" by Center for Human Rights Education 1997 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - "Murder in Carroll County" 1993 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - "NOW and Women of Color" 1988 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - "NOW Opposes Apartheid" in National NOW Times undated (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - "One Vote Cannot Erase South African History" in World-Herald, Omaha, Nebraska 1994 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - "Police Brutality or Police War?" in Peace & Freedom 1993 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - "The Politics of Attitude" undated (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - "The Politics of Color in the Feminist Movement" at 9th Annual Anti-Rape Week POWER Panel October 17, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - "Population, Consumption, and the Environment" response letter in Amicus Journal 1994 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - "Population Solutions Must Come From Below, Not on High" undated (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - "Practicing Freedom: Human Rights Education" in Sojourner: The Women's Forum 1996 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - "Raising Our Voices" in "From Abortion to Reproductive Freedom: Transforming a Movement" Ed. Marlene Gerber Fried 1990 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - "Rape and Third World Women" 1981 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - "Reading Ophelia Through a Gender Lens," presentation as student at Agnes Scott College 2001 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - "Reproductive Choice and Technology" 1992 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - "Reproductive Freedom: Our Right to Decide" 1992 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - "Reproductive Health Policy and Africa: Control or Cooperation?" in TransAfrica Forum 1987 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - "Reproductive Rights and African American Women" 1993 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - "Response to 'Some Ideas on Conspiracy Theories for a New Historical Period' by Leonard Zeskind" in "Conspiracies: Real Grievances, Paranoia, and Mass Movements," ed. Eric K. Ward 1996 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - "RU-486: Are you Sure or RU Sure You Want It?" draft undated (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - "Salvadoran Women Endure Civil War, Strife, Poverty" in National NOW Times 1988 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - "The Secrets of the US Delegation to Nairobi" 1985 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - "The Shot Felt Around the World" in Essence 1989 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - "A Simple Human Right: The History of Black Women and Abortion" in On the Issues 1994 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - "Sisterhood in Sheets" book review of Kathleen M. Blee's "Women of the Klan," c. 1991 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - "The 'Sistersong Collective': Women of Color, Reproductive Health and Human Rights" in American Journal of Health Studies 2001 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - "Some Tired of Fighting Civil War, Again, in 21st Century" undated (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - "Stop Talking and Finish Women's Treaty" in USA Today 1996 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - "The Struggle for Reproductive Freedom: 'Our Bodies, Our Lives, Our Right to Decide'" 1992 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "Third World Women and Rape" report from the First National Conference on Third World Women and Violence 1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "Third World Women and Violence" 1980 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - "Welfare, Scapegoating and Human Rights" speech given at Urban Justice Center, New York February 26, 1997 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - "White Nationalism and Immigration Today" in Network News 2001 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - "Why a Black Woman Fights for Abortion Rights" 1993 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - "Why Women of Color Can't Talk About Population" in The Amicus Journal 1994 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - "Women of Color: Population and the Environment" 1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - "Women of Color and the Feminization of Power" speech given at the National NOW Conference 1987 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - "Women of Color and the National Plan of Action workshop" at the 10th Anniversary Observance of the Spirit of Houston: A Decade of Achievement 1987 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - "Women of Color: An Invisible Decade of Growth" 1987 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - "Working with Minority Men Committing Violence Against Women" speech from the First National Conference on Third World Women and Violence 1980 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - "Yolanda Ward- in Memory and Tribute" (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Notes 1982-92, undated (Box 5, Folder 14-15)
  - "Programs and Publicity" 1989-94, undated (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - "Miscellaneous/ Untitled Writing 1993-1994 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence 1991-96, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)
- SERIES IV. ORGANIZATION FILES
  - Adult Association for Black Youth -African American Women's Networking Club 1986-93, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - African Art Collective Project -Aid to Imprisoned Mothers 1986-93, undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Alan Guttmacher Institute 1985-86, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - All African People's Revolutionary Party - Alliance Against Women's Oppression 1983-88, undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - American Association of Retired Persons 1984, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)